# 大家好 我們來放 放地籠
Hi everyone! We're put, putting the traps,
# 抓點魚回去那個我們家的那個池子里面養
to catch some fish to the, I mean, the pond at our site.
# 我們家的池子裡面魚都沒有啦
There's no more fish in our pond now,
# 一條都沒有
not even one.
# 全部 全 全部都被吃完啦
They've, they, they've all been eaten up.
# 現在到河裡面來 抓一點魚去
So we're coming to the river, to catch some fish back home.
# 就這裡
Right here
# 帶了點餌料 給它吃 把那魚騙進去
I have some bait, for the fish, to deceive them into the traps.
# 沒東西吃它不進的
They won't go into the traps otherwise.
# 你看 加下去
Look! I put the bait here,
# 一個地籠加一點點
a tiny little bit into each trap.
# 把這個地籠放在這邊
Let me put this trap here,
# 這邊水比較深一點
as the water is deeper here.
# 來來來來 有好吃的啦
C'mon, c'mon, c'mon! Here is some good food!
# 這裡的東西很好吃的哦
The food here is really tasty, you know.
# 哇 這個誰的魚釣
Wa! Whose fishing hook is it?
# 肯定是你們的 又去釣魚
It must be one of you guys'. You went fishing again,
# 沒釣到
but couldn't catch any.
# 這裡還有個大的
Here's another one, a big one.
# 專抓大魚 (註︰原字幕缺失)
It's specially designed for big fish.
# 加一點配料下去 (註︰配料.....不管了，照翻譯吧)
Let me put some ingredients.
# 現在那個網已經放下去了 我們明天早上再過來收
So now we've put the two traps there. Let's come again tomorrow and get them back.
# 現在
Now,
# 現在我們準備回去啦
now we're getting ready to go back.
# 第二天
The next day
# 今天我來收過個網 昨天放下去的
Today we're getting back the traps, that we put yesterday.
# 不知道有沒有魚
Let's see if there are any fish.
# 就在這前面這裡
It's right here in the front.
# 哇 好多啊
Wa! A lot!
# 你看
Look!
# 一大籠都是
It's full of fish!
# 不過就是小的
But they're are all small.
# 泥鰍
Loaches,
# 小魚
and small fish
# 哇 全是泥鰍
Wa! All are loaches.
# 這些泥鰍也是靚哦
These loaches are really beautiful.
# 拿桶裝點水去
Let me get some water with the bucket.
# 哎呀 有魚
Aya! Fish!
# 這裡就看得到魚啦
I can already see the fish here.
# 有泥鰍
Loaches,
# 這泥鰍怎麼好多鑽這裡來
why did so many loaches squeeze in?
# 你看這泥鰍
Have a look at these loaches!
# 哇
Wa!
# 好大的蛇頭魚呦
What a huge snakehead fish!
# 有 有 有 有 三條
Not, not, not, not one but three!
# 你看
Look!
# 又有泥鰍
Loeaches,
# 又有鯽魚
"ji yu" (local carps)
# 這蛇頭魚
And this is a snakehead fish.
# 這個蛇頭魚夠大啦
This snakehead fish is really big.
# 放到簍子上去
Put them onto the basket.
# 哇
Wa!
# 你看
Look!
# 夠大啦
Big, aren't they?
# 好大 這個
It's, really big!
# 這條最大
And this is the biggest.
# 放在這裡來
Let me put them here.
# 你看 收獲滿滿
Look! A fruitful day
# 這個桶沒白帶
My effort of bringing this bucket is well paid,
# 那麼一大桶
by such a huge bucket of fish.
# 好啦 回去啦
Alright! Let's go back.
# 剛好兄弟家的魚缸 他不要啦
It just so happens that my buddy has a fish tank and he doesn't want it anymore.
# 這是山泉水哦
This is spring water.
# 把那水引下來
I'm catching the water to the tank,
# 讓魚喝上山泉水
so that the fish can enjoy the spring water.
# 增加它的肉質 更鮮美
This can enhance their texture, and taste.
# 等裝滿水了把魚放上來
I'll bring the fish here after filling up the tank.
# 嗯 你看 留了這個竹節啊 它可以把這個泥巴過瀘掉
Um, look! Keeping the bamboo joint here can filter out the mud.
# 到時候我們換一下再把這個丬乾淨就行啦
Then we can simply replace it, and rinse it.
# 這樣泥巴就不會掉 直接掉到那裡去
So the mud won't be falling, falling into the tank directly.
# 把這個魚放進去
Let me put the fish into the tank.
# 蛇頭魚 放裡面去
Snakehead fish, into the tank
# 哇
Wa!
# 爽不爽 這個
Cool, isn't it?
# 大房間哦
Big room!
# 這裡也有條
Here's another one.
# 這三條都放到這裡面
I'll put all these three here.
# 再放一些小魚
Some small fish too
# 你看 那麼多小魚
Look! So many small fish
# 我放在魚缸裡面
Let me put them into the tank,
# 讓它們生活在一起
so that they can live together.
# 來 你們自由啦
C'mon! You're free now.
# 你看 好多這小魚哦
Look! A lot of this kind of small fish
# 發脾氣啦
It's angry.
# 這麼好的地方你們不要
Why don't you like this place? It's so nice!
# 那麼多食物哦
Here's a lot of food.
# 你看
Look!
# 你這轉來轉去的 它們
They're going round and round and round here.
# 很喜歡這裡哦
They love this place.
# 這裡有鬥魚
Here are fighting fish,
# 有花鯽魚
"hua ji yu" (local carps)
# 有蛇頭魚
snakehead fish,
# 有泥鰍
and loaches.
# 你看 這個蛇頭魚呀 它喜歡吃肉的
Look! This snakehead fish, it loves meat.
# 它就只吃肉的 它不吃素的
It doesn't eat any veggies, only meat,
# 很喜歡吃不魚的
small fish, in particular.
# 你看 這些泥鰍啊 這些鯽魚 可能都是變成了它們的盤中餐 (註︰不想再注音鯽魚了)
Look! These loaches, together with other small fish, may become their meals.
# 我們也很喜歡吃肉
We love meat too.
# 那麼快
So fast
# 搞了一個這個遮陰 遮陰網
I've fetched a shade, a shading net.
# 來蓋一下它們 要不然它們全跑了
I'll cover them up. Otherwise, they would all run away.
# 先把下面這一個先蓋一下
Let me cover this lower one first.
# 嗯 可以
Um! Alright!
# 你看
Look!
# 它們過得很開心哦 這樣子 又有山泉水喝
They can now live merrily here. I mean, they can enjoy the spring water.
# 下次我們吃魚的就跑來 在這裡抓
Next time when we want a fish for our meal, we can simply come here, and catch one.
# 多好啊
Nice!
# 好啦 今天的視頻到這裡了
Alright! The video ends here.